Okay בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף daf is ע"ז, Ayin Zayin,
77, we God-willing will finish the פרק perek today. We start two
lines from the bottom on ע"ו עמוד ב'. Ayin Vav Amud Bet.
We're dealing again with the משנה, Mishnah, wrapping it up, with yesterday's
talk about if the husband sort of stipulated (I'll talk in a
minute about if he stipulated or not anyway) that there wouldn't be
any blemishes, and there were blemishes, his wife had blemishes, but there's
a question when she got them, before or after the קידושין. kiddushin.
So if it's in the house of her father, it's her burden
of proof, and in her house, in his house it's his burden
of proof. And the גמרא Gemara sort of compares that to a
whatever, made this whole analogy of switching an ox, a donkey with
a cow,
and selling a cow to a שוחט shochet and where it got
back, it became a טריפה. treifa. And it's interesting that it held
up essentially two different models. One is that the burden of proof
is always on the person who's trying to extract the money, המוציא
מחבירו עליו הראיה. hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya. But the other is the
model of our משנה, Mishnah, which is that the burden of proof
is in the possession, you know, in terms of where the problem
was discovered.
And that sort of is at least how the גמרא Gemara ends
the whole story with the שוחט shochet as well, you know. So
if the שוחט shochet finds that the cow he bought from is
a טריפה, treifa, meaning he hasn't paid the money, if the problem
was discovered in his רשות, reshut, it's his burden of proof to
prove that they had occurred earlier. So again, that's interesting using, you
know, in contrast to our normal assumption that it's המוציא מחבירו עליו
הראיה hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya in terms of who's trying to extract
money. And then we end up with the last
lines here on ע"ו עמוד ב', Ayin Vav Amud Bet, דחמינו ממומין
שבסתר, dechaminu mimumin shebeseter, that's about things that are in private and
that cannot, are not exposed. That's where רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says
basically that this is going back to the fact that, excuse me,
that the חכמים Chachamim say that if it's things that were obvious,
or that were גלוי, galuy, that maybe could have been obvious, he
could have seen, then we assume that things are okay with it.
And then they even go so far to say, and even things
that are like under the clothes, if there's a bathhouse, then he
could have checked with his relatives that go to the bathhouse and
therefore things that he could have known about, we presume that he
did, and if he didn't say anything, then we presume he's okay
with it. So the גמרא Gemara says the following: אמר רב נחמן,
amar Rav Nachman, דניכפא, denichpa, somebody who has epilepsy, like a fainting
spell, כמומין שבסתר דמי. kemumin shebeseter dami. That's like something that's in
private because basically, as רש"י Rashi says (let's see the next line
of the גמרא), Gemara והני מילי דקביע ליה זמן, vehani milei dekvia
lei zman, that's if there's a fixed time for it. Because then
she can be sure that not to be seen by him when
she's (you know) during the period when she would have these spells,
and therefore she might have been able to keep it in hiding.
אבל לא קביע ליה זמן, aval lo kvia lei zman, if it
didn't have a fixed time, כמומין שבגלוי דמי, kemumin shebegaluy dami, it's
like something that was in public because then there was no way
she could have reasonably hid it since there's no way of predicting
when it would happen. Okay, so therefore he can't complain that 'hey,
I didn't know about this'. If it's something that we assume was
something she could have reasonably kept hidden, then we assume that he
didn't know about it or should have known about it. Now, I
want to say one thing before we get to the next משנה
Mishnah because the next end of the פרק perek is going to
continue with this issue of מומין. mumin. I have been explaining these
cases, if you remember about that he made a specific, she made
a specific stipulation that he doesn't have any blemishes. But you might
remember that the משנה Mishnah basically that started the whole thing was,
he said על מנת שאין בך מומין, al menat she'ein bach mumin,
on the condition that you have no blemishes, ונמצא בה מומין, venimtza
bah mumin, and then it's found she has blemishes. And then it
says כנסה סתם, kinnesa stam, if he marries her without saying anything,
like at the חופה chuppah without saying anything, then we have a
question about whether she gets the כתובה ketubah or doesn't get the
כתובה, ketubah, etc. So the גמרא Gemara had a question whether that
was building on the previous case (he stipulated at the time of
the קידושין kiddushin 'no blemishes' and then he had the חופה chuppah
without saying anything), or was it a case by itself, that even
in a case where he didn't say anything, right, כנסה סתם וכנסה
סתם. kinnesa stam ve-kinnesa stam. And if we read it the second
way, that the whole second case was independent, that he didn't say
anything from beginning to end, and he could divorce her, you know,
without paying the כתובה ketubah if she's got blemishes, then that actually
means that even without stipulating anything, if a woman has certain blemishes,
the husband is entitled to divorce her, right? So that's pretty radical
in terms of that. And we already spoke yesterday about the question
about like what the גמרא's Gemara assumption is in terms of if
the man's got a problem, do we assume that the woman would
more tolerate problems with the husband than the husband would tolerate problems
with the wife? So just one thing and I'm going to talk
about the הלכה halakha in a minute, what the, you know, how
the רמב"ם Rambam and the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch rule, just to
appreciate that it's possible through everything we've been talking about, even without
any stipulation, if there are these types of problems, at least the
מומין שבסתר mumin shebeseter (something that we would say that reasonably he
can say that he wouldn't have known about), then even maybe without
a stipulation he's entitled to say 'oh well I never would have
married her under those circumstances' and even if maybe the קידושין kiddushin
is binding if he didn't stipulate, at least he's entitled to divorce
her without paying the כתובה. ketubah. Okay, well I'm going to talk
about
the...
Wait, on
the epilepsy case, Sarah, how is it? The end of epilepsy at
Montefiore?
And
she has to make sure that before their epilepsy inpatient service they
don't have two guys from the or two women from the same
group from the same site because it will damage their שידוך shidduch
prospect.
Okay, good to know. So here we go, that's the idea of
the בסתר. b'seter. Okay. האיש שנולדו בו מומין, Ha-ish she-noldu bo mumin,
אין כופין אותו להוציא. ein kofin oto lehotzi. Now if a man
has blemishes and the blemishes occurred afterwards, like, you do not force
him to divorce his wife. His wife basically has to tolerate a
husband that's got blemishes. Okay. Now, אמר רבן גמליאל במה דברים אמורים
במומין קטנים. Amar Rabban Gamliel, bameh devarim amurim bemumin ktanim. That's by
small blemishes.
אבל במומין גדולים כופין אותו להוציא, Aval bemumin gedolim kofin oto lehotzi,
we do force him to divorce his wife. Okay now, right, if
she wants to divorce him. תוספות Tosfos of course says it's to
force if you want to force a divorce, it also means obviously
paying a כתובה. kesuva. She doesn't have to tolerate her husband with
those types of conditions. Now, of course with the man, right, we
don't talk about if the wife has blemishes after the marriage, okay,
there's no idea about forcing him to divorce, if he doesn't like
her, he just divorces her, right? So, right, so you don't need
this mishna. The point of the question about the woman was if
she had the blemishes before the marriage, he doesn't have to pay
the כתובה. kesuva. Okay, because I never would have wanted it under
these circumstances, etc. It's seen as basically his fault, my fault, so
he doesn't pay the כתובה. kesuva. But if the blemishes happen after
the marriage, he's entitled to divorce her, but he would still have
to pay
the כתובה. kesuva. Okay, so in this case also if he's got
the blemishes, okay, he divorces her and he pays the כתובה. kesuva.
Yes, does this apply also if he comes back from war and
he suffered a terrible injury? Is that
considered like within the rubric of מומין mumin as it were? In
other words, she doesn't want to live with him anymore because he's
lost...
Yeah, yeah, and that would be included, yeah.
But what about the מארס m'arser though? We didn't discuss this here.
Is it... I mean he had them to begin with, right? Meaning
he was a מארס m'arser and
he was נולדו בו, noldu bo,
what about if, you know, he had them to begin
with?
Well what difference, I mean, you mean about whether the קידושין kiddushin
would be binding to begin with. So that gets to Akiva's question
that we had yesterday, right, for אחרי עובר שבת, achrei over Shabbos,
which is, is it by him you could say that, what do
you call it,
so that's exactly the point, right? We learned over שבת Shabbos that
if in a case where basically if she's got problems, it could
be אינה מקודשת eina mekudeshes or if he has certain problems, we
still say that the קידושין kiddushin is binding and that's exactly because
of this different standard. So if she had the problems from before
the קידושין, kiddushin, right, whether there is or isn't a תנאי tnai
in certain circumstances we'd say she's אינה מקודשת. eina mekudeshes. If he
had the problems before the קידושין, kiddushin, at least if he took
care of them, he went to a doctor and healed them or
whatever, we'd say she still is מקודשת mekudeshes because she's still willing
to... because the גמרא's Gemara assumption that they can tolerate a lower
standard of a husband which again creates more problems in terms of
making, you know, גט get and עגונה agunah issues much more difficult.
Let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara and then we'll talk
about the הלכה למעשה halacha l'maaseh about this. וגרסינן תני נולדו. Vegarsinan
tany noldu. So Yehuda takes our mishna we have it, which is
that he got the problems
afterwards. וחייא בר רב תני היו Vachiyah bar Rav tany hayu that
he had the problems even before the wedding. מאן דאמר לאו פשיטא
היו. Man d'amar lav p'shita hayu. Yeah, yeah. מאן דאמר נולדו. Man
d'amar noldu. So if the point is that when he got the
problems
later we don't force him to divorce his wife according to the
תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, כל שכן היו. kol sheken hayu. Certainly if
he already had those problems we won't force him to divorce his
wife. דחזייא וקבלה. Dehazyei vekibla. She saw the problems presumably and she
was okay with it. אבל מאן דאמר היו, Aval man d'amar hayu,
but the one who has the גירסא girsa that if he had
the problems from beforehand according to the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma we
have to divorce him, force him to divorce his wife, אבל נולדו,
aval noldu, but in the case he got the problems later, well,
we would force him maybe because she was never okay with it
and she's now stuck in this marriage and she wouldn't want to
tolerate it, so maybe we would force him in that case. Okay
so that's an important question whether the גירסא girsa is היו hayu
or נולדו. noldu. Maybe by נולדו noldu we do force a divorce.
תנן, Tnan, now let's look back in the mishna. אמר רבן גמליאל
במה דברים אמורים במומין קטנים. Amar Rabban Gamliel, bameh devarim amurim bemumin
ktanim. By small blemishes. אבל במומין גדולים כופין אותו להוציא. Aval bemumin
gedolim kofin oto lehotzi. Big ones we would force him. בשלמא למאן
דאמר נולדו,
Bishlama leman
d'amar noldu, if the case is new problems, היינו דשני בין גדולים
קטנים, hainu d'shani bein gedolim ktanim, then he could say, you תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma say that new ones are not a problem, I
say new ones if they're big enough are a problem and we're
forced to divorce him. אלא למאן דאמר היו, Ella leman d'amar hayu,
but if we're talking about the pre-existing problems and the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma says that he was okay, she implicitly accepted. Then he
could say, you תנא קמא Tanna Kamma say that new ones are
not a problem; I say new ones are big enough for a
problem and we're forced to force him to the divorce. And מאן
דאמר הוו, man d'amar havu, if we're talking about the pre-existing problems
and the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says it's that he was okay,
he implicitly accepted it, so how what's the logic of the טעמא
מעולם? ta'ama me'olam? מה לי דזימנין מה לי דזענין, Mah li d'zimnin
mah li d'za'anin, who gives divorce and often without and she accepted
it? הסברה וקיבלה. Hasavrah vekiblah. What would be any logic to say
that if it was something that was pre-existing, we could now force
a divorce? She knew what she was getting into. This says no,
even if that's true, סבורה היא שהיא יכולה לקבל ועכשיו אינה יכולה
לקבל. Savrah hi shehi yacholah lekabel ve'achshav einah yacholah lekabel. Even if
it's a problem, even though she thought she would be okay with
it, it turns out she was in love at that time and
she was all, it was very heady in terms of the romance
and all that other stuff. She thought at the time, she persuaded
herself it would be okay. But it turns out that she wasn't
able to tolerate it. So therefore, we can still come and judge
that the קידושין kiddushin wasn't binding at the time she was okay
with it, but we can say that right now we view it
as something that objectively is not tolerable. And the fact that she
said she'd be okay with it earlier can't be held against her
if it's something that is really a big problem. That's
the logic of רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. Exactly.
Okay. ואלו מומין
גדולים. Ve'eilu mumin gedolim.
Now what are the big blemishes that רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel would say that we would force a divorce? פירוש
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Perush Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, he's the one
who makes the distinction between big and small size. כגון נסמית עינו,
Kegon nismit eino, there you go, brother-go, an eye became blind. נקטעה
ידו, Niktah yado, or a hand got cut off. נקטעה רגלו, Niktah
raglo, or a foot... oh. Yeah,
that in those days is not so well.
Is
he intact? He just can't walk so well.
Exactly. רב אבא בר יעקב אמר רבי יוחנן הלכה כרבן שמעון בן
גמליאל, Rav Abba bar Yaakov amar Rabbi Yochanan halacha keRabban Shimon ben
Gamliel, which means that in some places, maybe even cases where it
was pre-existing, but certainly if it's a new problem and it's big
enough, we're going to force a divorce. Okay. ורבא אמר רב נחמן
הלכה כדברי חכמים, Verava amar Rav Nachman halacha k'divrei chachamim,
which means that we won't force a divorce, presumably even if it's
a new problem. Okay. I mean if you keep the גרסה girsa
known to... וכי אמר רבי יוחנן הכי והאמר רבה בר בר חנה
אמר רבי יוחנן בכל מקום ששנה רבן שמעון בן גמליאל במשנתנו הלכה
כמותו. Vechi amar Rabbi Yochanan hachi veha'amar Rabbah bar bar Chanah amar
Rabbi Yochanan bechol makom sheshanah Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel bemishnatenu halacha kemoto.
Wherever רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel appears in the
משנה, Mishnah, we rule like him. And here רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says if it's a big problem we force
a divorce. חוץ חוץ, Chutz chutz, except for three cases: ערב וצידן
וראיה אחרונה, Areiv vetzidan vera'ayah acharonah,
for those of you who don't want to go into it. Anyway,
we basically rule like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel.
That's what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says. So how could רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan say that we rule like the חכמים? Chachamim? So the
גמרא Gemara says, אמוראי נינהו ואליבא דרבי יוחנן. Amora'ei ninhu ve'aliba d'Rabbi
Yochanan. There's a debate of אמוראים Amora'im according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan whether we always go like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel or not. And this last opinion says we don't. So
here you've got two issues, and the גמרא Gemara seems to,
at least logically, if you combine the two strict readings of the
גמרא, Gemara, it would be even if it's a new blemish and
even if it's a big one, we're not going to force a
divorce. Okay? So again, if the husband's got a problem with his
wife, it could be that אינה מקודשת einah mekudeshet altogether. And certainly,
for some women,
even if he would have to and even if he is מקודשת
mekudeshet and there's a new problem with his wife, he can certainly
divorce her as long as he's going to pay the כתובה. ketubah.
Whereas if she's got a problem with the husband, right, even if
it's like a type of thing that's significant, she's stuck. Okay, so
that's certainly a very big difference. And besides the fact that if
the problem was pre-existing, it might not be enough to say that
there was no קידושין, kiddushin, as opposed to when it's a pre-existing
problem of hers. So there's definitely a serious asymmetry going on here.
I want to keep on reading and then I'll sort of talk
about the bottom line, how the רמב"ם Rambam rules about this. So
let's take a look at the next משנה. Mishnah. ואלו שכופין אותו
להוציא. Ve'eilu shekofin oto lehotzi. And those that as opposed to a
big blemish according to the חכמים Chachamim we don't force a divorce,
there are some things that are so bad that we will force
a divorce if it's a problem with the man. What are they?
מוכה שחין, Mukei shechin, if he is filled
with boils. ובעל פוליפוס, Uva'al polipos, and this, we'll talk about what
this problem
is. ובעל פוליפוס, Uva'al polipos, a person who's got פוליפוס, polipos, which
the גמרא Gemara basically will say is basically somebody who
has constant runny mucus from his nose. והמקמץ, Vehamikametz, a gatherer, which
the גמרא Gemara will say is someone like gathers excrement as a
job. So
that's not very nice odors. והמצרף נחושת, Vehametzaref nechoshet, or smelter, והבורסי,
vehabursi, and a tanner. These are extremely
smelly and disgusting jobs. בין שהיו עד שלא נישאו, Bein shehayu ad
shelo nis'u, whether they existed before the marriage, ובין משנישאו נולדו, Uvein
mishenis'u noladu, and even after or certainly if they came after the
marriage. ועל כולן אמר רבי מאיר, Ve'al kulan amar Rabbi Meir, and
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says about all of them: אף על פי
שהתנה עמה, Af al pi shehitnah immah, not only if it existed
before the marriage, even if he explicitly stipulated with her and said,
"Look, I want you to agree, you're agreeing to marry me knowing
that I've got this condition or knowing that I've got this job,"
and she said, "Yes." Nevertheless, יכולה היא שתאמר, Yacholah hi shetomar, she
could say, סבורה הייתי שאני יכולה לקבל ועכשיו איני יכולה לקבל, Savrah
hayiti she'ani yacholah lekabel ve'achshav eini yacholah lekabel, like the גמרא Gemara
quoted before. I thought I could manage and now well could be
and now I can't manage, okay, and I realize I can't tolerate
it. So basically the, when it's things that are in this category...
even if, even if they're called מומים גדולים, mumim gedolim, like cysts,
disfigurements, like injuries or whatever, then even if it was known some
beforehand, whether before or after, excuse me, even
afterwards the חכמים Chachamim you don't force a divorce. But things like
this, these are seen as so intolerable that even if she explicitly
said she's okay with it, if she starts to say she's not
okay with it, we will force a divorce. And presumably force him
to actually pay the כתובה. ketubah. Now תוספות Tosafot asks Michael's question.
תוספות Tosafot asks וכי יכולה היא לומר איני יכולה לקבל קצת אם
כן כל נשי דרמאים vechi yecholah hi lomar eini yecholah lekabel ketzat
im ken kol neshei daramayin to say and then they'll give her
the כתובה. ketubah. If you say that forcing a divorce means that
he has to pay the כתובה, ketubah, so every woman will agree
to marry this abrit-tanner, okay, and then so make an explicit like
a prenuptial agreement and say that she's okay with it, and then
well, I feel like I'm not okay with it. Okay, so eventually
she'll say איני יכולה לקבל eini yecholah lekabel and get, she'll and
get שמא במקום שיש חשש רמאות אין לה כתובה. shema bimkom sheyesh
chashash rama'ut ein lah ketubah. תוספות Tosafot
says maybe that's up to the judges to decide and if they
see that she's just doing this, I mean obviously we might still
force the divorce but we might not pay the כתובה ketubah if
we think that the whole thing was a, was a, you know,
was a scheme. Alright, so now let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. So at least there's some cases we force a divorce.
So the גמרא Gemara says the following. מאי בעל פוליפוס? mai ba'al
polippus? What is this person with פוליפוס? polippus? אמר רב יהודה
אמר שמואל ריח החוטם. amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel rei'ach hachotem. Okay,
with some type of... oh, I'm sorry, I'm sorry. וחכמים אומרים וחכמים
אומרים מקבלת היא על כרחה. veChachamim omrim veChachamim omrim mikabelat hi al
karchah.
Excuse me, thank you. If the woman explicitly agreed, that was what
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says. But the חכמים Chachamim say if she
explicitly agreed then she's bound but then, you know, we're not going
to force a divorce. She explicitly agreed. חוץ ממוכה שחין, chutz mimuke
shechin, that's the one case of the guy that's got the blisters,
boils, מפני שממקטו mipnei shememakto and causes both... basically as he's having
sex with it it's the condition, okay, and causes his skin to
deteriorate or something. So that's the one case in which we'll force
a divorce and even if she, maybe even if she, you know,
for his benefit? Exactly. So basically even when we say she's stuck
straight like the חכמים Chachamim here that reject or to some extent
reject רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, the only case we'll force a divorce
is if it's a new condition and one of these extremely serious
ones. But if it's one that's big but not as big as
this, or if it was an existing, pre-existing and she was okay
with it, she's stuck with it. מעשה בצידן ma'aseh veTzidan is a
case in Tzidan. בבורסי אחד, beborsi echad, with a certain tanner שנפטר
לו אח בורסי, sheniftar lo ach borsi, and he had a brother
who was a tanner. אמרו חכמים amru Chachamim and the sages say
יכולה היא
שתאמר yecholah hi shetomar she could say to this guy who's next
in line to do יבום, yibbum, לאחיך הייתי יכולה לקבל ולך איני
יכולה לקבל. le'achicha hayiti yecholah lekabel ulecha eini yecholah lekabel. I was
okay with your brother in this disgusting profession because I really loved
him but with you I, I am not okay with it.
Which you wouldn't app that of the יבום.
yibbum. No, she can't, not if she doesn't want to. It's eventually
his choice whether to do יבום yibbum or חליצה. chalitzah. So in
this case basically since she has to express that she does not
want him to do יבום, yibbum, presumably the rabbis will force him
to do חליצה, chalitzah, okay. That's the point about that. Is they're
forcing you to... they won't force or whatever, but you know, if
he basically refuses to do חליצה, chalitzah, you know, I mean it's
not clear right what happens if you... I mean there was a
whole big תוספות Tosafot discussion there before, you know, we're not going
to force him, like we're not going to force sex on her.
But here we might eventually force him to do חליצה chalitzah if
we think that יבום yibbum is the proper path. But here we'll
basically agree with her and therefore we're really going to strongarm him
to do חליצה chalitzah instead of being between יבום yibbum or חליצה.
chalitzah.
Exactly. Okay. מאי בעל פוליפוס? mai ba'al polippus? What is this guy
this פוליפוס polippus that would be in this big problem category? אמר
רב יהודה אמר שמואל ריח החוטם, amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel rei'ach
hachotem, like a, a smell from the nose, so some type of
a body odor. במתניתא תנא ריח הפה, bematanita tana rei'ach hapeh, bad
breath. By the way it's quite interesting, right? So the big problems
of רבי שמעון בן גמליאל Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel about like a
broken off line in the eye or a broken leg, that we
wouldn't force a divorce, okay? I mean that's like an injury or
disability, but maybe that's not something that we feel that the wife
can't tolerate. Whereas, you know, something about like the bad breath and
the body odor or whatever, most of these things in the משנה
Mishnah had to do with things that were like maybe noxious, right?
It wasn't just an issue of a disability, right? So these types
of... so that's, you know, it's interesting that that's in a more
severe category. במתניתא תנא ריח הפה. bematanita tana rei'ach hapeh. רב אסי
מתני איפכא Rav Assi matni ipcha and רב אסי Rav Assi teaches
the opposite, that רב יהודה אמר שמואל Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel says
the bad breath and the ברייתא braita teaches the smell from the
nose. I don't know what a smell from a nose is, anyway.
וסימנך vesimanech and he gives him an indication and a mnemonic, שמואל
ואוקמיה לקול קולן. Shmuel ve'ukmiyeh lekol kolan.
שמואל Shmuel what never stop from talking about this whole perek so
that you remember שמואל Shmuel and the mouth, so שמואל Shmuel is
the one that says it's bad breath. Okay. המקמץ, hamikameitz, the one
who
gathers. So מאי מקמץ? mai mikameitz? What's he gathering? אמר רב יהודה
זה מקבץ צואת כלבים. amar Rav Yehuda zeh mikabetz tzo'at kelavim. Somebody
who gathers dog excrement.
So רש"י Rashi says what is... why would you need dog excrement?
So רש"י Rashi says, as we look at
רש"י, Rashi, המקמץ צואת כלבים מאוסה היא לו וצריך לה, hamikameitz tzo'at
kelavim me'usah hi lo vetzarich lah, המקמץ hamikameitz dog excrement that's about
he... no, he needs dog... excrement and he's basically he's showing to
them how the בגדים לפני כיבוסן יום או יומיים begadim lifnei kibusan
yom o yomayim that somehow they were used in laundering. You'll figure
that out. Interesting of course it never occurred to רש"י Rashi that
you might need someone to clean up the dog excrement because you
don't want dog excrement on your sidewalk. I think that's a very
modern invention.
Okay. תוספות Tosafot basically points out that you could be using dog
excrement for the tanning process which actually ties into the next discussion.
מתיבי, Meitivei, asks גמרא Gemara on this, מכדי מקמץ בורסי הוא. michdi
mikameitz borsi hu. We say that a מקמץ mikameitz is a בורסי
borsi and not dog
excrement. והתניא Vehatanya המקמץ והמצרף נחושת והבורסי, hamikameitz vehamitzaref nechoshet vehaborsi, it
lists the
מקמץ mikameitz different from the בורסי, borsi, so clearly מקמץ mikameitz is
not a בורסי. borsi. לא קשיא, Lo kashya, that's not difficult, כאן
בבורסי דקא כאן בבורסי רבא. kan beborsi daka kan beborsi raba. You
could have a guy who is a major scale tanner and a
small scale tanner, maybe and תוספות Tosafot points out you know and
maybe they I don't know get different degrees of smelly or different
types of jobs they do. אלא
לרבי יהודה קשיא, Ela l’Rabbi Yehuda kashya, for Rabbi Yehuda it's difficult
because the ברייתא braita says that what do you call it, a
מקמץ mikameitz is a בורסי borsi and you're saying it's a guy
who collects excrement. Of course, תוספות Tosafot says I don't understand the
problem, the guy who's collecting the dog excrement is for the purpose
of tanning. It's not just to collect, it's exactly the same thing.
But the גמרא Gemara somehow thinks it's different and asks the question.
So the גמרא Gemara says תנאי היא, Tannai hi, it's a debate
of תנאים Tannaim on what this מקמץ mikameitz is. תניא מקמץ בורסי,
Tanya mikameitz borsi, a מקמץ mikameitz is a בורסי. borsi. ויש אומרים
זהו המקמץ צואת כלבים, Veyesh omrim zehu hamikameitz tzo’at kelavim, and others
say it's one who collects dog excrement. Fine.
ומצרף נחושת, Umitzaref nechoshet, המקמץ צואת כלבים hamikameitz tzo’at kelavim is a
problem but המקבץ צואת hamikabetz tzo’at something else?
No, we said that before. No, nobody's discussing anything else. I mean
we haven't mentioned anything else but we're just describing what this profession
was.
Right.
המקמץ והמצרף נחושת והבורסי Hamikameitz vehamitzaref nechoshet vehaborsi and the guy who
smelts copper and the tanner.
מאי מצרף נחושת? Mai mitzaref nechoshet? What is the guy who smelts
copper? רב אשי אמר חספי דודי. Rav Ashi amar chaspei dudi. Basically
the guys that beat out pots. So the guy who works with
molten copper in order to make the pots or whatever to make
things out of it, that's apparently very smelly. רבה בר בר חנה
אמר זה המכתש נחושת מעיקרו. Rabba bar bar Chana amar zeh hamachtesh
nechoshet me’ikaro. No, it's the guy who actually you know gets the
copper out of the copper ore from its very source and somehow
that also is a very disgusting profession, like a coal miner I
guess or
something.
Metal sulfides which
produces hydrogen sulfide, rotten eggs, good to know. Okay. All right.
תניא כוותיה דרבה בר בר חנה, Tanya kevataih deRabba bar bar Chana,
איזהו מצרף נחושת זה המכתש נחושת מעיקרו, eizehu mitzaref nechoshet zeh hamachtesh
nechoshet me’ikaro, the one who extracts copper from its source. As must
be understood, just heard it requires a lot of eggs smell. אמר
רב האומר איני זן ואיני מפרנס. Amar Rav ha’omer eini zan ve’eini
mefarnes. Now let's say a man says, so these are cases about
having a certain type of a disgusting profession which if it's too
much he can be forced to divorce. Now let's say a guy
just refuses to do his marital responsibilities. I'm not going to pay
for my wife's food and board. יוציא ויתן כתובה. Yotzi veyitein ketubah.
So there also he would be forced to divorce and pay the
כתובה. ketubah. Okay, that makes sense. He's not doing his responsibilities. It's
sort of like a מורד mored as opposed to like a מורדת.
moredet. אמר רבי אלעזר אמרה לשמעתא קמיה דשמואל. Amar Rabbi Elazar amrah
lishmata kameih deShmuel. Rabbi Elazar went and said this in front of
Shmuel. אמר שמואל אכסוהו שערי לאלעזר. Amar Shmuel achisuhu se’arei le’Elazar. Shmuel
said feed Elazar barley, go feed Elazar dog
food, okay. עד שכופין אותו להוציא יכפוהו לזון. Ad shekofin oto lehotzi
yichpuhu lazun. Once you're already there to force the guy, why force
him to divorce his wife? יכפוהו לזון. Yichpuhu lazun. Force him to
satisfy his marital obligations. If the guy is saying he's not paying
his wife's food bill or food, you know whatever, force him to
pay the wife's food bill. Why are you forcing a divorce in
that case?
ורב VeRav says back, no, אין אדם דר עם נחש בכפיפה. ein
adam dar im nachash bekififa. We said this before. A person is
not forced to live with a snake, you know, in the same
basket. Who wants to live with a guy who basically is only
going to pay the food bill because the בית דין Beit Din
is forcing him? It obviously means that there's an enormous amount of
animosity in the marriage and if the husband had to be forced
to willingly do it then they need to get divorced. Okay. So
that's interesting, right? So that means that even though we have the
פוטנציאל poten-tzial of forcing him to pay the food bill, that is
seen as intolerable and we would choose rather to force the divorce.
So again it's an interesting lesson in intolerable, right? All these smelly
and disgusting things are intolerable, not paying the food bill or only
paying the food bill if you're forced is intolerable as opposed to
some other things which are not intolerable. Okay. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like
this, כי סליק רב דימי, Ki salik Rav Dimi, when Rav Dimi
went up to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, אשכחיה לרבי בנימין בר יפת.
ashkecheih leRabbi Binyamin bar Yafet.
He found Rabbi Binyamin bar Yafet. דיתיב וקאמר לה משמיה דרבי יוחנן
Deyativ veka’amar lah mishmeih deRabbi Yochanan and he was saying this in
the name of Rabbi Yochanan that you force the divorce in that
case. אמר ליה, Amar leih, he said to him, על דא אכסוהו
שערי לאלעזר בבבל. Al da achisuhu se’arei le’Elazar beBavel. Because of this
they made Elazar eat dough, eat like you know dog food. or
cat whatever you know animal food in ברזא *barza* because he said
such a thing. אמר ליה Amar lei, רב אסי *Amar leih Rav
Assi*, okay, but anyway that's the debate right, or is that a
bad enough problem that we would force a divorce in that case?
אמר רב אסי *Amar Rav Assi* אין משיאין אלא פסולות *ein masin
ela hapsulot*, we only force a divorce in cases of a man
married to a woman who is פסולה *psula*, meaning who is not
allowed to be married to. Okay, like you know a כהן *kohen*
married to a גרושה *grusha*. Okay, but so it's coming to exclude
whom? Case what it's really coming to exclude is a case of
מומים mumin. *mumim*, like not having kids seems to be the focus.
תא חזי בדיני דשמואל *Ta chazi bedinei de-Shmuel*, when it's said to
שמואל *Shmuel*, אמר *amar*, he said, כגון אלמנה לכהן גדול *kegon almanah
le-kohen gadol*, like an אלמנה *almanah* married to a כהן גדול *kohen
gadol*, גרושה וחלוצה לכהן הדיוט *grusha ve-chalutzah le-kohen hedyot*, or a divorcée
to a normal כהן *kohen*, ממזרת ונתינה לישראל *mamzeret u-netinah le-Yisrael*, or
a ממזרת *mamzeret* married to ישראל *Yisrael*, or בת ישראל לנתין ולממזר
*bat Yisrael le-netin u-le-mamzer*, or a ישראל *Yisrael* woman married to a
ממזר *mamzer*. אבל *aval*, case where it's only a prohibition to be
married, אבל *aval*,
what's it come to exclude? It's not coming to exclude the cases
of the מומים mumin *mumim*, here's what it's coming to exclude. נשא
אשה ishah ושהה עמה עשר שנים ולא ילדה *nasa isha ve-sha-ah imah
eser shanim velo yaldah*, a man was ten years with a woman
and didn't have kids, אין כופין אותו *ein kofin oto*, they do
not force a divorce. Even though and it's what, yes, yes, even
though they're supposed to have kids and there's a מצוה *mitzvah* of
פרו ורבו *pru u-revu*. In that case, like you know, if there's
not being an active transgression and they both want to be married,
I guess it's a case in the משנה mishna, *Mishnah* where it
was like intolerable for the woman. This is not a case where
it's intolerable for the woman, meaning it's not like the woman is
coming and saying "I want to have kids, let me get a
divorce so I can marry another man to have kids." That would
be a different story. Here the case is that the husband and
wife are both totally okay with the marriage. Like this is how
it's different. Until now, one of them was not happy. My wife
has a מום *mum*, my husband has a מום *mum*, he's got
this disgusting job, they want to get divorced. Husband doesn't want to
divorce without paying the כתובה ketubah *ketubah*, or the wife wants to
force the husband to get a גט *get*. Here, everybody's happy, it's
just a כהן *kohen* married to a גרושה *grusha* or a couple
married without kids, but they're both totally happy to stay in the
relationship. We as the רבנים *rabbanim* are going to say "Oh, we
don't like it, we object, we're going to force a divorce." So
it's one thing to come along with a happy marriage and force
a divorce if they say they're actively violating, as opposed to just
not being מקיים *mikayem* the מצוה *mitzvah* פרו ורבו *pru u-revu*. So
we will, you know, we will sort of in-, you know, force
a divorce or interrupt this very happy marriage if there's an active
violation, but not if it's just that they're not doing פרו ורבו
*pru u-revu*. Okay. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like
this. אבל התחליפא בר דימי *aval Ha Tachlifa bar Dimi* אמר אפילו
נשא אשה עשר שנים ולא ילדה כופין אותו *amar afilu nasa isha
eser shanim velo yaldah kofin oto*, no even in that case we
force a divorce. תנן *Tnan*, now let's take a look. We learned
in the משנה mishna *Mishnah*: אלו שכופין אותו להוציא *Elu she-kofin oto
lehotzi*, the following we force a divorce: מוכה שחין ובעל פוליפוס *mukei
shechin ve-ba'al polipus*, and we don't mention, you know, these other cases
about married to like a כהן *kohen* and a גרושה *grusha* or
not having kids. בשלמא לרב אסי *Bishlama le-Rav Assi*, according to רב
אסי *Rav Assi*, that you don't do it for lack of kids,
so it's good, it's not a problem that we don't mention the
case about the, what do you call it, about the כהן *kohen*
and the גרושה *grusha*. כי הני דקתני *ki hanei de-katani*, we mention
problems that are like the רבנן *rabbanan* sort of see as problematic,
people with these various blemishes. דלאו אלו *de-lav elu*, but we're not
dealing with cases of biblical violations, that's a different category.
אלא להתחליפא בר דימי *ela le-Tachlifa bar Dimi*, according to התחליפא *Tachlifa*,
why not mention the case of not having kids? And that's not
even a biblical obligation, not even like a passive, you could argue
that that's not even the passive non-fulfillment of פרו ורבו *pru u-revu*,
because in theory he could always marry another woman, but there's nothing
stopping him from marrying another woman. So there's no actual violation going
on here, you know. So why is this not mentioned? Tell me,
told you the answer, because it's a question about whether the couple
themselves is happy with this or not. Because if we actually would
force a divorce for non פרו ורבו *pru u-revu*, why isn't this
listed in our משנה mishna *Mishnah*? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
like this. אמר רב נחמן לא קשיא *Amar Rav Nachman lo kashya*.
הא בדברי הא בשוטי b'shotei? *Ha bedevari ha beshoti*. There's a difference.
Are we going to do it with words, persuasion, or are we
going to do it with sticks? Okay, are we going to try
to beat, you know, with actual physical force? So even if we're
going to force a divorce in the case of not having kids,
we're only going to try to do it through persuasion. We're not
going to try to do it with actual use of force. And
therefore it's not listed in the משנה mishna. *Mishnah*. The משנה mishna
*Mishnah* is talking about where we use force.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, מתקיף
לה רבא *matkif lah Rava*, בדברים לא יוסר עבד *bedevarim lo yivaser
eved*. Now רבא *Rava*, according to a תוספות *Tosafot* sort of, he
quotes a פסוק *pasuk* in משלי *Mishlei*, a slave will not be
remonstrated, will not, you know, be chastised through words, you know. People
that are
obstinate and resistant, you gotta use force. Okay. So therefore he says,
if you're going to call me כופין *kofin* by the case of
not having kids, it would have to mean כופין *kofin* with force.
There's no logic of כופין *kofin* without force, that's just not going
to succeed. So therefore we're back to square one: If we use
force in the case of not having kids, why not mention it
in
our משנה mishna. *Mishnah*? אלא אמר רבא *ela amar Rava*... If both
the idea you use force by not having kids, we'll use more
force. Okay, but here's the difference. התם, hatam כי אמרה ki amra
הא זינא ha zina ובהדי שפיקנא. u'v'hadei shafkinan. In the משנה, mishna
if she says I'm happy to stay married to him even though
he's got these problems, we let her. The משנה mishnah, until now
is only talking about forcing a divorce or not paying a כתובה
ketubah. if one of the parties is not happy. Okay, then that's
one thing. To say that a happy marriage we're going to interfere
with, that's a very different story. הכא, hacha, אף על גב דאמרה
af al gav de'amra הא זינא ha zina ובהדי שפיקנא, u'v'hadei shafkinan,
in the case of not having kids even if she says I'm
happy to stay married, לא שפיקנא לה, lo shafkinan lah, we do
not allow it. So that's the issue why the forcing the divorce
of the marriage is of a different category. And that's why some
say you don't force the divorce if there's not having kids, and
those that say that you do, still put it in a different
category. It's a category of even if the couple is totally happy
with it. So the גמרא Gemara says, wait a minute, is it
only in the משנה mishnah we force a divorce even if they're
totally okay with it? והרי מוכה שחין, ve'harei mukei shachin, the case
of the guy with the, you know, with the boils or whatever,
דאף על גב דאמרה de'af al gav de'amra הא זינא ha zina
ובהדי שפיקנא, u'v'hadei shafkinan, לא שפיקנא לה, lo shafkinan lah, even though
they're okay with staying married, we don't allow it because it'll hurt
him. So there we do interfere that's mentioned in the משנה. mishnah
The גמרא Gemara says חוץ ממוכה שחין מפני שממקתו, chutz mimukei shachin
mipnei shememakto, ודתניא התם. v'detanya hatam. So the משנה this case says
that we would interfere with even when they're happy, so why don't
we also list the case about not having kids? So the גמרא
Gemara. says no, התם כי אמרה ki amra הא זינא ha zina
בהדי בסעדי, b'hadei b'sa'adi, if she says look, I want to stay
married to him and we'll have witnesses, you know, we'll have separate
rooms and we'll have witnesses to make sure that we keep to
our separate rooms, we won't have sex with each other, okay? So
therefore and therefore there's not a problem that it'll injure him because
only the act of sex that injures him. In that case, שפיקנא
לה, shafkinan lah, we allow it. So that's interesting that we allow
them to continue to be married even though they're not having sex,
but if they're okay with it, they're okay with it, okay? But
הכא hacha in the case of not having kids, so אף על
גב דאמרה af al gav de'amra הא זינא ha zina בהדי בסעדי,
b'hadei b'sa'adi, even if she says I'll stay together with him with
witnesses, obviously that's not going to help. The problem
is
you're not having kids. Keeping separate bedrooms isn't going to help the
situation. So לא שפיקנא לה, lo shafkinan lah, we don't allow it.
So basically the basic point is that our משניות mishnayot are talking
about cases where there's an injured party, okay, or one party is
sort of, you know,
is suing for divorce. And then we can talk about we'll
get involved and force a divorce, or we'll get involved at the
husband's side, if he's the one suing for divorce then you don't
have to pay the כתובה. kesuvah. What about if they're happily married,
would we therefore, you know, interfere and say even though you're happily
married, we think it's not tolerable, you're violating
a prohibition, you're not having kids? So that's the debate. For violating
a prohibition we will get involved, for not having kids, that's debatable
whether we will or won't, but even if we do get involved,
it's going to be of a different category than
the, you know, than these other cases. Now, בשוטי? b'shotei. No, no,
בשוטי. b'shotei, It is going to be with physical force, but conceptually
it's a different category because this is a case where they want
to stay married and we're forcing ourselves in. So it wasn't listed
in the משנה. In practice, if you say you force a divorce
in the case of not having kids, in practice it will be
the same, we'll do it בשוטי, but the reason it was debated
and the reason it's not listed in the משנה is because it
was a happy marriage. Now, one minute. Now I want to tell
you something about the הלכה. halacha. First of all, in terms of
the case
of the what-do-you-call-it, in terms of this case about forcing a divorce,
okay, without the kid, the גמרא Gemara seems to conclude that we
do force it, at least that's the opinion and that is as
you saw with the little red by the case. There's an important
רמ"א, Rama, and the רמ"א Rama says like this,
the רמ"א Rama says, he says like this: so even if the
שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch paskens we force a divorce in case of
not having kids after ten years,
he says דבזמן הזה אינו מנהג לכוף כלל. d'bazman hazeh eino minhag
lichof klal.
Nowadays we don't have the practice to ever, like, force a divorce,
okay, the רמ"א Rama in אבן העזר Even Ha'ezer קנ"ד. kuf nun
dalet. Now the question is how far does that go? Does that
even go to a case of like of a, what do you
call it, of a marriage באיסור? b'issur? You know, I mean for
us, we don't force it ever, we follow the laws of the
state, so we're not using physical force to force anything here. But
when the Jews had sort of self-government, right, and they were using
physical force, right, so the רמ"א Rama says this, he says אינו
נוהג לכוף כלל eino noheg lichof klal by the case of פריה
ורביה periyah u'reviyah or just in general? Like we're not going to
force it, you know, you know, that's the, I mean, you know,
that's a different, that's an interesting question. So that's like one issue
about how much in practice did they make a, you know, did
they make a choice like, not because they weren't able to, they
had the power to, but they said like, you know, this is
not for us to sort of go ahead and interfere, specifically if
the marriage was a happy one. Meaning let's say it's a happy
marriage and the woman doesn't cover her hair.
When a marriage is happy, there's a general point that we're not
going to force a divorce even though the גמרא Gemara says you
do. In practice they didn't, whether that includes the case of like
a real violation of like כהן גרושה Kohen Grusha or whatever is
a different question. That's point one. I want to go back to
the other issue, which was this question about the difference between husband
and wife in the whole issue of מומים. mumin So let me
just read to you from the רמב"ם Rambam to give you a
sense of like the imbalance here about how we rule.
I'll just try and make sure I think I have two minutes
to do this. Hold on a second.
No, I mean because I got to get to the end of
the פרק. perek.
The only thing is,
okay, so wait a minute. Okay, so here's what the רמב"ם Rambam
says. He says, starts from just this is a brief recap of
things we've discussed. Okay, המוציא אשה סתם, Hamotzi Isha Stam, this is
in פרק כ"ה, Perek Chaf Hey, נמצאו עליה נדרים, nimtzu aleha nedarim,
תצא
בלא כתובה. tetze belo kesuvah. So he repeats what we remember even
if there is no stipulation, okay, so the קידושין kiddushin is still
binding, but she can be divorced without a כתובה. kesuvah. Okay, then
he discusses what type of נדרים. nedarim. וכן הכונס אשה סתם, Vechain
hakones isha stam, I'm reading an excerpt,
ונמצאו בה מומים, venimtzu bah mumin, מומי הנשים, mumei hanashim,
ולא ידע בהן במום זה, velo yada bahen bemum zeh, ולא שמע
בהן, velo shama bahen, הרי זו תצא בלא
כתובה. harei zo tetze belo kesuvah. So again, if there's no stipulation,
the marriage is still binding, but he's entitled to divorce her without
a כתובה. kesuvah. And then he goes on and discusses about the
bathhouse, מום שבגלוי mum shebegalui and מום שבסתר, mum shebeseser, and the
whole types of discussions in the גמרא. Gemara. And he has a
whole interesting issue here about let's say he doesn't have relatives in
the city, but he has friends. Can he ask his friends about
what they saw, checking out his potential wife in the bathhouse, or
is it only something he feels comfortable asking his relatives about? But
anyway, the point is even without stipulating anything, okay,
he's entitled to divorce her if there are מומים mumin or נדרים
nedarim without paying a כתובה. kesuvah. Okay, and then he goes on
and discusses about what if this debate when the מומים mumin came
about.
He says like this, one minute. Right, now if
he
has,
now if these were
all the מומים mumin there from before he got married, right, but
if the מומים mumin were after he got married, then basically we
say it just happened to you, it's not her fault, and you
know, if you want to divorce you're going to have to pay
the כתובה. kesuvah Right, so the whole point is that we're not,
of course, I'm not forcing a divorce, but he's entitled to divorce
without paying the כתובה kesuvah. like we've learned, all those cases is
when they weren't מומים mumin, prior to the marriage. If the מומים
mumin, came after they had got married, then okay, bad luck, things
happen, we all get old, people's things change or whatever, you want
to divorce her fine, but you'll have to pay כתובה. kesuvah. That's
her מומים, mumin? okay? So she's got the מומים, you didn't say
anything, if it was from before marriage then basically he, it's not
his fault, it's her fault, she should have told him or whatever,
he didn't want this, that wasn't the assumption, he's entitled to divorce
without a כתובה. kesuvah. After the marriage, things happen, so you want
to divorce, divorce, but you'll still have to pay the כתובה. kesuvah.
Now, how about if he's the one that has the מומים? It
says האיש שנולדו בו מומים Haish shenoldu bo mumin אחר שנשא achar
shenasa אפילו נקטעה ידו או נסמית עינו afilu niktea yado o nismis
eino ולא רצתה אשה לישב עמו velo ratsa isha leshev imo אין
כופין אותו להוציא וליתן כתובה. ein kofin oso lehotzi veleiten kesuvah. ואם
רצתה תצא Veim ratsa tetze תצא בלא כתובה כדין כל המורדות. tetze
belo kesuvah kedin kol hamordos.
So basically he's got these blemishes, something happened to him, she feels
it's intolerable, so he פוסק, paskens, you don't force him to divorce,
and if she basically says I absolutely refuse to live with him
anymore, fine, then she maybe we'll get him to divorce you, but
he won't have to pay a כתובה. kesuvah. Okay, now you could
say one minute, this is like it is exactly parallel, right? Because
if she gets the blemishes, if she gets the blemishes after the
marriage, if he wants to divorce her, he has to pay the
כתובה. kesuvah You can't blame her. Not blaming her means he still
has to pay the כתובה kesuvah. if he's going to divorce her.
So if he gets the problems after the marriage, you can't blame
him. If she wants to force a divorce, she can force a
divorce, but he won't pay the כתובה. ketubah. You can't blame him,
these are things that happened after.
is that אשה doesn't have the power like in one case he
has the power. In this case she doesn't have the power, right?
And the other case he can decide whether to divorce or not,
he's just completely sort of, but you know רמב"ם Rambam says no
actually we'd listen to her and we might force a divorce if
she says it's intolerable, but we would just say you can't blame
him for that so there's not going to be a כתובה. ketubah
Okay so it's not as, and then he says נשא אשה ושהה
עמה עשר שנים ולא ילדה כופין אותו להוציא ויתן כתובה. nasa ishah
vesha'ah imah eser shanim velo yaldah kofin oto lehotzi veyiten ketubah. Okay,
and he goes dot dot dot dot dot, right,
and then he gets to our משנה, but if you had these
problems and
one minute, ואלו שיוצאים שלא בכתובה המדיר את אשתו ושנמצאו בה מומין
וצרעת כופין אותו להוציא ויתן כתובה. ve'elu sheyotzim shelo beketubah hamadir et
ishto veshenimtzu bah mumin vetzara'at kofin oto lehotzi veyiten ketubah.
So bottom line is the way it works is the following, right,
with bracket the cases where he made a specific stipulation and the
קידושין kiddushin wasn't binding and it was like a מקח טעות, mekach
taut, okay? Because we're going to assume the קידושין kiddushin is binding.
So basically the conclusion of the סוגיא sugya is that if it
turns out she had these problems, she had problems that you would
say he wouldn't normally tolerate beforehand the wedding, nobody made any conditions
but she had these problems, then he's entitled to divorce her without
paying the כתובה ketubah. because it seemed like she was deceiving him
or wasn't what he expected at the time of the wedding. If
there were problems that came up later then that's not her fault,
then you want to divorce her, divorce her but pay the כתובה.
ketubah. And the reverse, if he's got these problems that
preceded the wedding basically, then and they were like of a serious
quality, right, dot dot dot, I'm sorry if he's got the problems
that preceded, no, not the scenario for the ones that preceded because
then we assume she saw them and she was okay with them,
we sort of like bracket that case, right, that gets back to
the גמרא Gemara that if he has certain problems then we assume
she's more okay with those problems, it's less of an issue. So
basically she says no, but that goes back to that גמרא Gemara
about that imbalance that we assumed women were more tolerant than men
are, but if he gets the problems afterwards, okay,
the same way that she gets the problems afterwards it's not her
fault and if he wants to divorce her, he divorces her but
pays the כתובה. ketubah. It's not his fault so we might force
a divorce, at least רמב"ם Rambam says if she insists, but he
won't have to pay the כתובה. Not his fault that he got
some condition afterwards. So there's some type of a parallel but the
problem, the difference would still show up if the problems existed at
the time of the wedding where he's more entitled to say I
don't want this and she's less entitled to say that she doesn't
want that.
Right, so it seems that if she thought she could tolerate it,
it's like we don't rule like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who says
that if she says she was okay she's okay, so she
even if she finds out later
she can't, right, that
we go against רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, so she definitely she does
not, right. So you listen to תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and the
משנה in חמש... Chamesh... ובירושלמי דף נ"ט ע"א... u'vi-Yerushalmi daf nun tet
amud alef... I don't know the difference. Okay let's keep on going
in the גמרא. Let's finish up this פרק. perek. Okay so משנה
says like this and then the סיפא seifa my gosh I'm only
eighty nine minutes okay. אמר רבי יוחנן סח לי אותו פחם מאנשי
ירושלים ושיטין הוו בידו של גט וספר תהילים עשרים וארבעה מוכי שחין.
Amar Rabbi Yochanan sach li oto pecham
me'anshei Yerushalayim veshitin havu beyado shel get vesefer tehillim esrim ve'arba'ah mokei
shechin. There are twenty four different types of skin disease very relevant
to
this coming פרשה parsha of מצורע. Metzora. וכולם אמרו חכמים תשמיש קשה
להם. vekulan amru chachamim tashmish kasheh lahem. All of them they said
sex aggravates the condition.
ובעלי ראתן קשה
מכולן.
uva'alei
ratan kasheh mikulan.
And those that have this condition of ראתן ratan is worse than
all of them. This is the condition that later on in the
גמרא it seems
like it's a problem about some type of a bug that entered
into a person's
brain or something or skull and somehow that causes some skin condition
apparently. Okay. מאי הוי? mai havay? What does this come from? ותניא?
vetanya? It says in a ברייתא, beraita, נא האי בעל ראתן המקיז
דם ושימש הוו ליה בנים ויתיקין. na hai ba'al ratan hamakiz dam
veshimesh havu leh banim vitikin. If somebody lets blood and then has
sex, his blood let from him and has sex, הוו ליה בנים
ויתיקין, havu leh banim vitikin, he'll have children that are weak. המקיזו
שניהם ושימשו הוו ליה בנים בעלי ראתן. hamakizu sheneihem veshimeshu havu leh
banim ba'alei ratan. If both had blood let then they had sex,
husband and wife, הוו ליה בנים בעלי ראתן, hamakizu sheneihem veshimeshu havu
leh banim ba'alei ratan, then they'll have these ראתן ratan children. אמר
רב פפא ולא אמרן אלא דלא טעים מידי. Amar Rav Papa velo
amran ela dela ta'im midi. The גמרא's talking about having sex right
after letting blood is only if you didn't taste anything right after
you gave blood they tell you to
eat something have to get a little sugar back in your system.
אבל טעים מידי לית לן בה. aval ta'im midi leit lan bah.
If he ate something we don't have that problem. מאי סימניה? mai
simaneih? What are the signs of that somebody has this condition? דלפן
עיניה ודייבין נחיריה. dalfan eineih vedayivin nechireih. The eyes tear flow and
also the mucus comes from the nose. ואשרי רירא מפומיה veisrei rira
mipumei and there's a spittle coming from the mouth and a fly
sort of hover around a person. ומאי אסותיה umai asutei so what
do you do in cure? אמר אביי amar Abaye פיני דדומא pinei
deduma גילדא דאגוזא gilda de'agoza וגילדא דאשפה vegilda de'ashpa so these types
of various I don't know food stuffs. I want to read it
because וטחלי דמלקי vetakhlei demalkei pink and crisp, a lot of them
are a particular flavor of
fine
grass, watermelon, וזהר של אגוז vezeher shel egoz the shell of a
nut and וגילדא דאגוזא vegilda de'agoza the shavings of a nutshell וגילדא
דאשפה vegilda de'ashpa the shavings of an ashpa which are a
high וטחלי
דמלקי vetakhlei demalkei what? וזמירי vzmirei ומתוכלא דדיקלא umthla dedikla
what's that? דדיקלא סומקא dedikla sumka סומקא sumka oh yeah, the cover
of some red unripe date. Okay, ושלקי להו בהדי הדדי vshalkei lehu
bahadi hadadei no no. Okay, and you boil them all together ומייתי
ליה לביתא דשישא umaytei leh leveita deshisha and you bring this person
into a house of marble because basically basically you want like a
sterile operating condition because you want to perform an operation, so you
don't want him to be exposed to the elements. Okay, דשישא deshisha
right? ואי לאו איכא ביתא דשישא ve'i lav ika beita deshisha if
there's no house of marble around, מייתי ליה לביתא דשב לבני ופלגא
maytei leh leveita deshav livnei ufalga you bring him into a house
that's the walls are so thick they're seven and a half bricks
thick. So basically you want it very protective from the elements. ושדו
ליה תלת מאה כסי vshadu leh tlat mea kasei you pour three
hundred cups of this boiled liquid on his head.
So the Gemara is exaggerating. עד דלייפה על אישתא דמוחיה ad dlayfei
al ishta demokhayei until the floor of his skull is you know
the hull of the skull is is softened because you're about to
do brain surgery. וקרעו למוחיה ukaru lemokhayei so you are you cut
open his his skull, okay, because you've softened it with this liquid
on it, with this hot liquid on it. ומייתי ארבע טרפי דאסא
umaytei arba tarfei de'asa you take four leaves from a myrtle and
then you've got this bug in his brain you know in the
skull that you're now going to remove and it's got four legs.
ומדלי חד כרעא umadlei khad kara and each you lift up each
leg of the bug ומותבי חד טרפא umotvei khad tarfa and you
put the leaf under the leg because if you try to remove
the bug before you put this leaf under its leg it's going
to grab on you know when you try to remove it. So
you have to have this thing underneath
as well. ושקלי ליה בציבתא vshakli leh betsivta you remove you take
a tweezer וקלו ליה בנורא ukalu leh benura and you burn the
bug.
ואי לא הדר אמרן ve'i la hadar amran if you don't burn
the bug he'll just jump back into the guy's head.
Okay, מה אמר רבי יוחנן ma amar Rabbi Yochanan Rabbi Yochanan announced
היזהרו מזבובי של בעלי ראתן hizaharu mizvuvei shel ba'alei raatan keep your
distance from the flies of the ba'alei raatan because that's probably the
reason. Now I don't know if my husband has an idea, spreads
the disease, let's take a look. רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira what did
he say about Ba'alei Raatan? רבי זירא לא הוה יתיב בזיקא Rabbi
Zeira la hava yativ bezika Rabbi Zeira would not sit sick in
the same area of the you know of the wind that would
carry from from the people with this disease. So they understood you
know the concept of contagious disease. רבי אלעזר לא עייל באהליה Rabbi
Elazar la ayel be'ahaleih Rabbi
Elazar didn't go into the same tent. Okay, רבי אמי ורבי אסי
לא הוו אכלי מביעי דההוא מבואה Rabbi Ami veRabbi Assi la havu
akhlei mibeiei de'hahu mavoa they wouldn't even eat some eggs that were
from that same courtyard. You know somehow they were afraid that things
that things were contagious. רבי יהושע בן לוי מיכרך בהו Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi mikhrakh behu now Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi didn't care about
this. He would he would like you know intertwine like involve himself
with them, literally wrap himself among them. ועסיק בתורה ve'asik baTorah and
he would learn Torah and he said the Torah protected him. אמר
אילת אהבים ויעלת חן amar ayelet ahavim ve'ayelet khen it is the
doe of our love and you know and the right exactly the
beautiful doe. Exactly. Okay, and like a you know jewelry of charm,
חן. khen. מה איילה זו חן ma ayala zu khen
if it brings charm if it brings you know onto those that
learn it, אמינא מגיני מגינה היא עליהם amina magini magina hi aleihem
and it protects them from any injury. So the Torah protected me.
What can I tell you. One also wonders you know if this
is a little bit of like also of a response or how
much is this in the context also of those stories in the
gospels of Jesus who would go amongst all of the sick and
the lepers and so on and the Pharisees would avoid them. So
here you have Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi who's willing to go among
them as long as he's learning Torah. כי הוה שכיב ki hava
shakhib when he died אמרו ליה למלאך המות amru leh lemalakh hamavet
so they up in heaven said to the angel of
death זיל עביד ליה רעותיה zil avid leh re'uteih go do for
him his desire, which is a funny euphemism, basically means kill him
but it also seems to be like you're going to tell him
because it's time to die but also maybe like you know a
seat whatever he requests he might have. This seems to be the
story too. אזל ואיתחזי ליה azal ve'itkhazei leh right, so the angel
got to appear to him. אמר ליה אחוי לי דוכתאי amar leh
akhvei li dukhtai so Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi says show me my
place. עולם הבא. Olam HaBa. It's so funny, that's where he's going,
but okay, he wanted a preview. אמר ליה לחיי, Amar lei le-chayei,
fine. אמר ליה הבו סכינך. Amar lei havu sakinech. So then he
said to the angel of death, give me your knife before we
go up to see עולם הבא Olam HaBa because I'm afraid that
you're going to kill me along the way. דילמא מבעתת לי באורחא,
Dilma miv-at-at li be-orcha,
maybe you're sort of scaring me with your knife along the way.
Anyway, I want to feel protected while we're going on this trip.
יהבי ניהליה, Yahavei nihaleih, so the angel of death gave him his
knife. כי מטו להתם, Ki matu le-hatam, when they came to עולם
הבא, Olam HaBa, דלייה, Dalyei, he lifted up the curtain or whatever
and he saw what his place would be like. כמהוי ליה, Ke-machvei
lei, and when he was showing it to him,
שוור, Shavar, so Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi jumped over the fence. נפלה
לההוא גיסא, Nafal le-hahu gisa, and he fell on the other side
of the fence, he jumped into עולם הבא Olam HaBa while he
was still alive. He wanted to save himself from actually the experience
of dying, so he wanted to enter in alive into
עולם הבא. Olam HaBa. נקטיה בקרנא דגלימיה, Naktei be-karnei de-glimei, so the
angel of death grabbed onto him by the edge of his cloak.
אמר ליה בשבועתא דלא הדרנא, Amar lei bi-shvuata de-la hadarna, Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi said in an oath I refuse to return to that
world.
אמר קודשא בריך הוא, Amar Kudsha Brich Hu, God comes and says,
אי איתשיל אשבועתא, Ei it-shil a-shvuata, if he ever had an oath
annulled while he was living, הדר, Hadar, then we're going to annul
this oath and he'll have to go back. His oath, you know,
won't stand. ואי לא, Ve-ei lo, but if he never annulled an
oath, לא הדר, Lo hadar, then he's not going to be bound
to go back. He made an oath and he's going to be
allowed to keep it. So אמר ליה, Amar lei, so he managed
to go into עולם הבא Olam HaBa without dying. So אמר ליה
הבו לי סכינאי, Amar lei havu li sakina'i, so the angel of
death says give me back my knife. לא יהב ליה, Lo yahav
lei, he wouldn't give it back to him. נפקא בת קול ואמרה
ליה, Nafka bat kol ve-amra lei, so a heavenly voice came out
and said, הב ליה, Hav lei, give the angel of death back
his knife. דמתבעי לברייתא, De-mit-bei le-biryata, because it's needed for the creatures
because other people have to die. You managed to get in alive
and maybe you want to keep the knife because then nobody else
can get killed. No, you got in alive but the angel of
death needs his knife. Okay. מכריז אליהו קמיה, Machriz Eliyahu kameih, so
Eliyahu announced in front of him, פנו מקום לבר ליואי פנו מקום
לבר ליואי, Panu makom le-bar Liva'i panu makom le-bar Liva'i, clear the
place for the son of Levi, for Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. עד
דאשכחיה לרבי שמעון בן יוחאי, Ad de-ash-chechei le-Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai, until
he found Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai, דהוה יתיב על תלת עשר תכתי
דדהבא, De-hava yativ al tlat esar tachtei de-dahava, who was sitting on
thirteen stools of gold. אמר ליה את הוא בר ליואי, Amar lei
at hu bar Liva'i, so Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai said, are you
the son of Levi? אמר ליה הן, Amar lei hen, he said
yes. אמר ליה אתחזי לך קשת בימיך, Amar lei it-chazei lach keshet
be-yomecha, so Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai
says did you ever
see a rainbow in your life? אמר ליה הן, Amar lei hen,
yes. אמר ליה אם כן לאו בר ליואי את, Amar lei im
ken lav bar Liva'i at, if so, you're not Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi and you don't deserve all the honor they're giving you. Because
why did he ask that? Because a rainbow is the אות ברית
ot brit that God, you know, remembers and doesn't destroy the world.
So the understanding is that if you have a real צדיק tzadik
in your generation, there won't be a rainbow because there's no need
for a rainbow because the righteousness of the צדיק tzadik protects his
generation. The Maharsha also points out that if you ever violated a
שבועה, shvuah, so the presence of a צדיק tzadik that never violated
a שבועה shvuah is enough to help God keep his שבועה shvuah
and you don't need a rainbow to keep God from remembering his
שבועה shvuah to not destroy the world. So he said did you
ever have a rainbow? אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said to him,
הן, Hen, yes. אם כן לאו בר ליואי את, Im ken lav
bar Liva'i at, if so, you're not Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi and
you don't deserve all the honor they're giving you. ולא היא, Ve-la
hi, the Gemara says you know what, it's not true. דלא הוי
קשת בימיו, De-lo havei keshet be-yamav, there never was a rainbow in
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi's life. He really was that righteous that there
was no rainbow in his life.
ולא הוי מידי, Ve-lo havei midei, there was nothing. אלא סבר לא
אחזיק טיבותא לנפשאי, Ela savar lo achzik tivuta le-nafshai, he said I
don't want to make myself, you know, give myself all this credit,
so he didn't want to admit to the fact that there was
no rainbow in his life. Okay, one more story. רבי חנינא בר
פפא, Rabbi Chanina bar Pappa, שושביניה הוה, shushbineih hava, Rabbi Chanina bar
Pappa was, he's a friend. There's a question as to whose friend
was he. Was he Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi's friend or was it
the מלאך המות's Malach HaMavet friend? Okay, anyway, כי הוה קא ניחא
נפשיה, Ki hava ka nicha nafshaeih, when Rabbi Chanina bar Pappa was
dying, אמר ליה מלאך המות, Amar lei Malach HaMavet, he said to
the angel of death, זיל עביד ליה רעותיה, Zil avid lei re'uteih,
go do what he desires.
אזל לגביה, Azal lagabeih, he went to
visit him. אמר ליה שקלי קוסי יומא דהדא תלמודי, Amar lei shakli
kosi yoma de-hada talmudi, so the first thing he said was, ask
for a quest of thirty days to review all of my learning.
דאמרי אשרי מי שבא לכאן ותלמודו בידו, De-amri ashrei mi she-ba le-chan
ve-talmudo be-yado, for they say praised is the one that comes here
and his learning is in his hand. So therefore I want to,
you know, have all my learning under my belt before I die.
שבקיה, Shavkyei, he gave him the time. לבתר תלתין יומי, Le-vatar taltin
yomei, after thirty days, אתחזי ליה, It-chazei lei, he appeared to him.
אמר ליה אחוי לי דוכתאי, Amar lei achvei li duchtay, he said
show me my
place. אמר ליה לחיי, Amar lei le-chayei, fine. אמר ליה הבו סכינך,
Amar lei havu sakinech, he said to him give me your knife
before we go on the trip. דילמא מבעתת לי באורחא, Dilma miv-at-at
li be-orcha, lest you scare me. אמר ליה כחברך דחמשת לעבד רבי
יהושע בן לוי, Amar lei ke-chaverach de-chamsht le-avad Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi,
you want to do to me like your friend, like what Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi did to me? אמר ליה, amar lei, so he
said to him, אייתי ספר תורה, Aiti sefer Torah, I'll bring a
ספר תורה, sefer Torah, וחזי מי איכא מידי דכתיב ביה דלא קיימתיה,
Ve-chazei mi ika midei de-chtiv beih de-la kiyamteih, and say, see is
there anything that is written in the Torah that I didn't fulfill.
I'm just as worthy as Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, so you need
to give me your knife as we go on this trip.
אמר ליה מי אדבקת בבעלי ראתן, Amar lei mi adbakt be-ba'alei ra'atan,
he said to him, did you
ever sort of involve yourself with the people that have this contagious
disease, ראתן, ra'atan, and went on to study Torah? Now that there
it sort of makes you think about those health workers that are
going out there, yeah,
where do they get that, like, you know, ability to risk their
lives, you know, and whatever? So he said right, מדריגה, madriga, you're
not there. Okay, so he
says דאפילו הכא, d'afilu hacha, even though he wasn't at that מדריגה,
madriga, כי נח נפשיה ki nach nafshia when he died, איפסיק ליה
עמודא דנורא בין דידיה לעלמא, ifsik lei amuda de-nura bein didey l'alma,
a pillar of fire separated him between himself and the rest of
the world. Beside
his coffin, who was
it again? רבי חנינא בר פפא Rabbi Chanina bar Pappa and everybody
else to show that he was like in his own מדריגה, madriga,
he was in a separate, you know, level than everyone else, בין
דידיה לעלמא. bein didey l'alma. וגמירי, u-gemiri, and we have the tradition
דלא מסיק עמודא דנורא d'lo masik amuda de-nura
that a pillar of fire only separates אלא לחד בדרא, ela l'chad
bedara, only on somebody who is single in his generation, או לתרין,
o l'trein, or two people in a generation. Now they have this
pillar of fire, but they
gotta bury him, so קרב גביה לא איחזק karve gavei lo achzak
went close to the coffin. אמר ליה, he said, עשי בשביל כבוד
חכמים, asai bishvil kvod chachamim, lower the pillar of fire for the
sake of the honor of the sages. לא אשגח, lo ashgach, he
didn't pay attention. I don't know who is the he, the angel
of death? I don't know who it is. עשי בשביל כבוד אביך,
asai bishvil kvod avicha, sounds like it was the most, because he
said do it for the honor of your father, lower the pillar
of fire. לא אשגח, lo ashgach, he didn't pay attention. עשי בשביל
כבוד עצמך, asai bishvil kvod atmecha, do it for your own honor
because we gotta bury you.
מיד איסתלק, mi-yad istalek, fine, the pillar of fire went away so
they could bury him. But it was clear that he was in
a separate category. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, לאפוקי ממאן דאוקימיה l'afukei mi-man
d'okimay as you
point out yourself says לאפוקי, l'afukei, the reason the pillar of fire
is there is to keep out of his boundary somebody that did
not fulfill
even דאפילו אות אחת d'afilu os achas even one letter of the
תורה, Torah, wasn't at the same מדריגה madriga as רבי יהושע בן
לוי. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. אמר ליה רב אדא בר מתנא, Amar
lei Rav Adda bar Matna, לאפוקי ממאן? l'afukei mi-man? So who are
you asking, who are you looking at? לאפוקי
ממר דאית ליה ציצית במדריגה, l'afukei mi-mar d'it lei tzit tzit b'madriga,
people like you, like the Master, דלא אית ליה מעקה באיגרא, d'lo
is lei ma'aka b'igra,
you don't have a fence on your roof! You know,
so, you know, you're not at that level to treat other people.
ואיני, v'eini, but actually that was not true, הדר, hadar, he did
have a fence on his roof, והשתא דשדיא זיקא, v'hashata d'shadya zika,
that time that he was making that comment, a wind blew it
down and he hadn't got around to putting it back up, but
maybe also, you know, not being that whatever. Anyway, so still speaking
about like all these different degrees of, you know, of health. אמר
רבי חנינא, Amar Rabbi Chanina, למה אין בעלי ראתן בבבל? lama ein
ba'alei ra'atan b'Bavel? Why are there none of you בעלי ראתן ba'alei
ra'atan in בבל? Bavel? משום דאכלי סילקי mishum d'achli silki because they
eat beets, ושתי שיכרא דהיזמי v'shashei shichra d'hizmei and they drink the
mead of היזמי hizmei of a certain type of a shrub. אמר
רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, למה אין מצורעים בבבל? lama ein metzoraim
b'Bavel? Why are there no מצורעים metzoraim people with skin disease in
בבל? Bavel? משום דאכלי סילקי mishum d'achli silki because they eat beets,
ושתי שיכרא v'shashei shichra they do beer, ורחץ במי פרת v'rachatz b'mei
Prat and they bathe in the Euphrates. הדרן עלך המדיר את
אשתו.
Hadran Alach Hamadir
es Ishto. Yeah,
yeah. הדרן עלך המדיר, Hadran Alach Hamadir, yeah, yeah.
I think so, yeah.